You wouldn't believe me, but we will be
solving 12 different problems in just a
single video. How do we do that? And
that is through the magic of patterns.
Let us find out all about them. Hello
friends, welcome back to my channel.
You might be wondering what happened all
of a sudden. Why are we focusing on
patterns? If you remember my previous
video, I briefly talked about how it is
very difficult to go over each and every
problem statement that is available on
lead code. Also, if you're preparing for
your interview, how far do you solve
problems? How many problems do you
solve? This is actually very very
tricky. And if you think about it, while
solving all of these problems, you might
have realized there are so many
recurring patterns. You might have
realized that hey, I have already
applied this pattern before. So that is
why we understand patterns and how you
can use them. Basically the idea over
here is that you try to identify some
recurring problems. If you have noticed
I always talk about what other similar
problems you can find out and that is
why because you see these kind of
patterns repeated. So if you have solved
one problem of a kind, you are able to
solve other problems also. And once you
have started to find out all of these
patterns, as soon as you're given a
problem, your mind starts to work. You
can think about okay, I can apply this
approach or I can apply this approach.
And when you see such kind of a question
in an interview, you are able to speed
up your process as well because over
there you do not know what can come your
way. But if you are prepared about
something to look for then it becomes
easy to solve and it is very real life
scenario as well. If I tell you okay
just find a treasure in a whole lot of
area then you don't even know what to
look for. But if I tell you that the
treasure is of green color then you
exactly know what to look for. At least
you have a starting point. And that is
exactly what patterns mean when you come
across coding problems. They really help
you to speed up your process and it will
guarantee you interview success as well.
So first of all, where do we start? The
most basic pattern that you might have
already seen and done at a lot of places
is the two pointers pattern. The idea
over here is very very simple. For
example, you have an array like this.
What you do is instead of iterating over
every element, you take up two pointers
and iterate over them simultaneously. So
what you can do is if you have your
array like this, you can take up two
different pointers and now you move
these pointers as per your need. What
you can do is you can move one of the
pointers one step at a time and at the
same time you can move the other pointer
two places at a time or anything that
works for you. The other way you can use
a two-pointer pattern is let us say you
were given an array. Now the common
method is that you start from the
beginning and then try to traverse your
array. Correct? with two pointers. What
you can do is you can also have another
pointer that is starting from the very
last of your array. So once again
whatever is the problem statement based
upon that you can start to iterate
through your array from both the
directions. So it is kind of giving you
a starting point. You are given a
problem statement and now you are
wondering okay if I'm iterating one step
at a time how do I get the next element?
And that is where you can think okay to
get the next element either I can start
one more pointer from the beginning or I
can start one more pointer somewhere
else in the array also. So what does all
of that mean? For example, let us try to
look at the problem twosome. In this
particular problem, you are given a
sorted array and now you are said that
find me two numbers which equal the sum
of a particular number k. How do you
solve this problem? Certainly there's a
brute force way. But with a two-pointer
approach, what you can do is you can
start off one pointer over here and you
can start off one pointer over here. You
do -5 + 6. So that will give you one.
Now this array is sorted. So what you
can do is if you want a bigger sum, you
can traverse the first pointer one step
ahead because you know that all the
numbers are in an increasing order. So
the sum is going to increase and if you
want to go towards a smaller sum then
you take this rear pointer and start
moving backward. So if you go over here
the sum is going to decrease. So what
you will do? You will keep on iterating
like this and this until you find your
particular sum that you need. So what
did we just do? We were able to apply
the twopinter approach to come up with
an efficient solution in just one
traversal of the array. Similarly, if
you remember, we also had a problem
called threesome. In threes sum, all you
need to do is fix one of the numbers
that you want to start with. And then on
the rest of the array, you again apply
the twosome approach. So once again,
you're taking the help of two pointers.
In the next iteration, you are going to
fix the other number and then once again
apply the twosome approach. So what can
you find over here? I was able to apply
this particular pattern of two pointers
to solve two different kind of problem
statements. The twosome problem and the
threesome problem. Let us keep going
ahead. One other problem that you might
have seen is you have to merge two
sorted lists. And what is happening? You
are given two sorted arrays and now you
have to give me a resultant array that
is also sorted. Once again, where does
the twop pointer approach come in handy?
You start off one pointer here and then
you start off one pointer over here. And
now what you can do, compare both of
these elements. Whichever is the
smallest just add it to your result
list. And now you can advance your
pointer. Now compare minus5 and minus1.
Minus 5 is smaller. So minus y will get
in your result. And then you are going
to advance this pointer forward. What
are we doing over here? Again, we apply
the two-pointer approach to perform only
one traversal of both of the lists and
ultimately we will have our entire
sorted list. Think about it. There can
also be a similar problem where you are
given two sorted arrays and you have to
remove the duplicates in between them.
So once again the method will remain the
same. You start off your pointers from
the starting positions and now keep on
iterating until you find duplicate
elements and just remove them instead of
iterating both the arrays again and
again. So do you really think these all
are separate problems? No, we are just
applying a similar pattern to all of
these problems. And another similar
problem that you might have found is
finding the intersection point of two
sorted arrays. Basically look at these
two arrays. This first array is a sorted
array and the second array is also
sorted. Up till here both these arrays
are different. But at this particular
element they merge and now they are the
same. Once again is this a different
problem to solve? No. You are again
applying the same pattern. You will keep
on iterating and as soon as you find the
same element, you will return your
answer. All of this seems very fancy,
right? But how can you actually identify
where can you apply the two-pointer
approach? If you think about it, most of
it comes from experience. But there are
certain keywords which you can look for
in a problem statement where this
twopinter approach may be applicable.
For example, as soon as you see a sorted
sequence, it immediately gives you one
advantage. the smallest element will be
on the left and the largest element will
be on the right. So if you want to do
something with the smallest element and
the larger element then immediately
apply two pointers or if you have to go
towards some kind of a target sum then
again it means that two pointers can
help you because you are getting a
minimum and a maximum. you don't have
anything beyond those limits and if
you're defining your limits that kind of
narrows down okay this will be the
efficient solution. Similarly when you
have to compare and combine elements
think about the previous case we had two
sorted lists you need to combine them.
One way to combine would be that you
pick up a particular element and then
iterate over all of the other list.
Correct? Or you can start both the
pointers at the same time and then keep
on combining them as you go. This saves
you time and it will be efficient as
well. Sometimes you might have realized
that when you are iterating through an
array, you might have wondered okay if I
apply a nested loop as soon as this
thought comes to your mind, it means
that at least you can try two pointers.
A nested loop simply means that you are
fixing one element and then you're
iterating over all of the other
elements. So it could be possible that
if you apply two pointers and iterate
over the elements together maybe you
have a faster approach right away
available over there. And the last
whenever you have to move or shrink a
window. So two pointers are essentially
giving you a operating window in
between. So you have fixed two limits.
You may want to sum all of the different
numbers in this particular interval
based upon if you want a larger sum or a
smaller sum. You can modify your two
pointers. So these are some of the key
points that you should look out for. I'm
not saying that this is an exhaustive
list and certainly the more problems you
solve the more easily you will be able
to identify them. Let us keep moving
ahead and find out more applications.
You can apply the two-pointer approach
even to strings. For example, take this
problem. You have to find out if a
string is valid wrong. One way to do is
that you iterate from the beginning and
go all the way up to the end. You found
a string. Now start from the very last
and then again go all the way to the
beginning and then you compare both
these results. The other efficient way
will be that you again take up two
pointers starting from the first element
and the right character. Now if both of
these are same what you can do is you
can move your pointers simultaneously
one step forward and one step backward.
Again compare both of these elements. So
keep on going until both of your
pointers merge. If you have merged both
the pointers and every character matched
what did it mean? this string was a
palendrome. Otherwise, if at any
condition, let us say this string was X.
A and X do not match. So, you can stop
right over there and say that this
string is not a parend row. It saves you
so much time rather than iterating
through the entire string both the
times. What other problem comes in your
mind when you think about a string and
two pointers from the starting and the
beginning? Yes, you can also reverse a
string. And similarly what you can also
do is you can also reverse a certain
section of your string. So basically let
us say this is my particular string. I
have to reverse this part in the middle.
I take up two pointers like this. And
now I'm just going to swap both of
these. As soon as I swap it, I'm going
to move one step forward. And then once
again I'm going to swap both of these.
So we are solving the same problem again
and again. You just have to take up two
pointers and then there are so many
different combinations possible. Up till
now we have been advancing both of these
pointers with the same speed either in
the forward direction or in the reverse
direction. Remember I told you that you
can advance these two pointers with
different speeds as well. And that is
where you might have already seen a
similar problem come across your way.
You are given a link list and you have
to find out the middle element. So how
you can do is you have this link list
over here. You start off both the
pointers from the same position. Now the
first pointer will be a slow pointer and
the second pointer will be a fast
pointer. A slow pointer means it will
only move one step at a time and the
fast pointer will move two steps at a
time. So what happens at every
iteration? The slow pointer moves here.
The fast pointer moves here. The slow
pointer moves here. The fast pointer
moves here. Slow move here. And the fast
move here. As soon as the next of the
fast pointer is null, you can stop over
there. And what just happened? Look at
your slow pointer. It is pointing at the
middle element. And why is that? So it
is very very obvious. Let us say you
have a link list only of three elements
where the last element is null. If you
start from the beginning and you have
two pointers, if the first pointer takes
two steps, the slow pointer will only
take one step. So the slow pointer is
always at the halfway of the fast
pointer. And that is the underlying idea
how you can use pointers with different
speeds to arrive at an efficient
solution. On a similar concept, you
might have also heard about the problem
finding a cycle in a link list.
Basically, what happens is one of these
nodes will be connected to some other
node in your link list. And to find this
cycle, you will keep on moving both of
your pointers and you are guaranteed
that they will meet somewhere. Because
if you think about it in a race if one
of the person is moving faster and it is
a loop ultimately the faster person will
catch up with the slower person.
Correct? So once again these two
pointers are helping you to find an
efficient solution. What else? You might
have also seen a problem where you are
given a array of zeros and ones and now
you have to separate them. That means
all the zeros should be on one side and
all of the ones should be on the other
side. That means you are partitioning
around a particular condition. So let us
say I have this array with me. Once
again I take up my two pointers. I know
that all of the zeros should be at the
left and all of the ones should be at
the right. So I have my zero over here
and this is fine. My zero is on the left
and my left pointer is good. So what I
will do is I will move ahead. As soon as
I move ahead, I see that I have a one
over here. One should not be on the
left. So I'll wait. Now look at the
right pointer. It is pointing at a one.
So one should be on the right. So okay,
I won't do anything.
Now go back one step. Again, I'm
pointing at a one. One should be on the
right. So once again, I won't touch it.
Now go one step backward. What do you
see now? I see a zero over here. Zero
shouldn't be over here. So now I have a
very good condition with me. I have one
pointer over here that shouldn't be and
I have one pointer over here that should
not belong here. So what do you do?
Immediately you swap both of them. So
what will happen? This will become a
zero and this will become a one. So both
of my pointers are now happy. And once
again I can move this one step forward
and this one step backward. Again one
should not belong here. and zero should
not belong here. So I will swap them
again.
So this way you are going to keep on
moving ahead until both of your pointers
meet and eventually all of the zeros
will be on the left hand side and all of
the ones will be on the right hand side.
So basically you're partitioning based
upon a certain condition and similarly
you might have also seen the Dutch
national flag problem where instead of
zeros and ones you have a zero a one and
a two. So what do you do in that case?
All of the zeros should be on the left
and all of the two should be on the
right. Any other element you know that
it will be a one. So let it stay in the
middle wherever it is. Another famous
problem that you might have encountered
is container with maximum water. You are
given an array and all the different
integers represent the height of that
particular wall. You have to find out
which container has the maximum water.
So what do you do again? Have a starting
pointer and have a ending pointer. This
is the maximum area possible. Correct?
So you cannot go beyond that. The only
option you have is to shrink the area
and then find out which container has
the maximum water. So these are some of
the hints that help you to decide that
if a two-pointer approach will work out
for me because these two pointers are
helping you to give finite limits that I
cannot have a solution beyond these. So
the only way left is that you either
need to converge or you need to move
both these pointers to the end such that
you are ensuring you have covered all of
the elements and most of the time they
guarantee you a solution that works in a
time of order of n. Isn't it interesting
how with just a single pattern we were
able to solve so many questions. What do
you think about this particular pattern?
What other problems have you found that
follow the same principle or a similar
idea? Tell me everything in the comment
section below and it will become a very
good collection to categorize all of the
similar problems that are working on the
same concept and I will be happy to
discuss if you have any other doubts
based upon this particular pattern. As a
reminder, if you found this video
helpful, please do consider subscribing
to my channel and share this video with
your friends. Also remember that now you
can schedule one-to-one sessions with
me. You can find the link in the
description below and schedule a
session. Also, a huge shout out to all
of the members who support my channel.
You guys really keep me going. And as a
member, you do get private reply to your
comments and early access to new videos
as well. Stay tuned for my upcoming
video. Until then, fear.